Chapter 17. The Ramadan.
As Quiqu's Ramadan, or fasting and humiliation, was to continue all day, I
did not choose to disturb him till towards nightfall. For I cherish the
greatest respect towards everybody's religious obligations, never mind how
comical, and couldn't find it in my heart to undervalue even a congregation
of ants worshiping a toad stool. Or those other creatures in certain parts
of our earth, who, with a degree of footminism quite unprecedented in other
planets, bow down before the torso of a deceased landed proprietor merely on
account of the inordinate possessions yet owned and rented in his name.
I say we good Presbyterian Christians should be charitable in these things and
not fancy ourselves so vastly superior to other mortals, pagans and whatn not
because of their half crazy conceits on these subjects. There was Que now
certainly entertaining the most absurd notions about Yojo and his Ramadan. But
what of that? Quiquake thought he knew what he was about. I suppose he seemed
to be content and there let him rest.
All our arguing with him would not avail. Let him be, I say, and heaven
have mercy on us all, Presbyterians and pagans alike, for we are all somehow
dreadfully cracked about the head, and sadly need mending.
Towards evening, when I felt assured that all his performances and rituals
must be over, I went up to his room and knocked at the door, but no answer. I
tried to open it, but it was fastened inside.
Quiqu said I softly through the keyhole all silent I say quiqu you speak it's Ishmail
but all remained still as before I began to grow alarmed I had allowed him such
abundant time I thought he might have had an apoplelectic fit I looked through
the keyhole but the door opening into an odd corner of the room the keyhole
prospect was but a crooked and sinister one I could only see part of the
footboard of the head and a line of the wall, but nothing more. I was surprised
to behold, resting against the wall, the wooden shaft of Quequ's harpoon, which
the landlady the evening previous had taken from him before our mounting to
the chamber. That's strange, thought I, but at any rate, since the harpoon
stands yonder, and he seldom or never goes abroad without it, therefore he
must be inside here, and no possible mistake.
Quiquang.
All still, something must have happened.
Applexi. I tried to burst open the door, but it stubbornly resisted. Running
downstairs, I quickly stated my suspicions to the first person I met,
the chambermaid. La, she cried. I thought something must be the matter. I
went to make the bed after breakfast, and the door was locked, and not a mouse
to be heard. And it's been just so silent ever since. But I thought maybe
you had both gone off and locked your baggage in for safekeeping. La ma'am,
mistress, murder, Mrs. Hussy, apoplelexi. And with these cries, she
ran toward the kitchen, I following.
Mrs. Hussy soon appeared with a mustard pot in one hand, and a vinegar crew in
the other, having just broken away from the occupation of attending to the
casters, and scolding her little black boy. Meantime, Woodhouse, cried I. Which way to it?
Run, for God's sake, and fetch something to pry open the door. The axe. The axe.
He's had a stroke. Depend upon it. And so saying, I was unmethodically rushing
upstairs again empty-handed, when Mrs.
Hussy interposed the mustard pot and vinegar crew it and the entire caster of her countenance.
What's the matter with you, young man?
Get the axe. For God's sake, run for the doctor, someone, while I pry it open.
Look here, said the land lady, quickly putting down the vinegar cuit, so as to
have one hand free. Look here. Are you talking about prying open any of my
doors, and with that she seized my arm?
What's the matter with you? What's the matter with you, shipmate? In as calm,
but as rapid a manner as possible, I gave her to understand the whole case.
Unconsciously clapping the vinegar crew it to one side of her nose, she
ruminated for an instant, then exclaimed, "No, I haven't seen it since
I put it there." Running to the little closet under the landing of the stairs,
she glanced in and returning told me that Quiqu's harpoon was missing. "He's
killed himself," she cried. "It's unfortunate Stigs done over again. There
goes another counter pain." God pity his poor mother. It'll be the ruin of my
house. Has the poor lad a sister?
Where's that girl? There, Betty. Go to Snarlles the painter and tell him to
paint me a sign with no suicides permitted here and no smoking in the
parlor. Might as well kill both birds at once. Kill. Ah, the Lord be merciful to
his ghost. What's that noise there? You, young man, have asked there. and running
up after me, she caught me as I was again trying to force open the door. I
don't allow it. I won't have my premises spoiled. Go for the locksmith. There's
one about a mile from here. But a vast, putting her hand in her side pocket.
Here's a key that'll fit, I guess. Let's see. And with that, she turned it in the
lock, but alas, Quiqu's supplemental bolt remained undrawn within.
Have to burst it open, said I, and was running down the entry a little for a
good start when the land lady caught at me again, vowing that I should not break
down her premises. But I tore from her, and with a sudden bodily rush, dashed
myself full against the mark. With a prodigious noise, the door flew open,
and the knob slamming against the wall sent the plaster to the ceiling. And
there, good heavens, there satwiqu, altogether cool and self-colcted, right
in the middle of his room, squatting on his hands, and holding yojo on the top
of his head. He looked neither one way nor the other way, but sat like a carved
image with scarce a sign of active life.
Quiqu said I, going up to him. Quiqu, what's the matter with you? He ain't
been sitting so all day, has he? said the land lady. But all we said, not a
word could we drag out of him. I almost felt like pushing him over so as to
change his position, for it was almost intolerable. It seemed so painfully and
unnaturally constrained, especially as in all probability he had been sitting
so for upwards of 8 or 10 hours, going to without his regular meals.
Mrs. Hussy, said I, he's alive at all events. So leave us, if you please, and
I will see to this strange affair myself. Closing the door upon the
landlady, I endeavored to prevail upon QuueG to take a chair, but in vain.
There he sat, and all he could do. For all my polite arts and blandishments, he
would not move a peg, nor say a single word, nor even look at me, nor notice my
presence in the slightest way.
I wonder, thought I, if this can possibly be a part of his Ramadan. Do
they fast on their hams that way in his native island? It must be so. Yes, it's
part of his creed, I suppose. Well, then let him rest. He'll get up sooner or
later, no doubt. It can't last forever, thank God, and his Ramadan only comes
once a year, and I don't believe it's very punctual. Then I went down to
supper. After sitting a long time listening to the long stories of some
sailors who had just come from a plum pudding voyage as they call it, uh that
is a short whailing voyage in a schooner or brrig confined to the north of the
line in the Atlantic Ocean only. After listening to these plum puddingers till
nearly 11:00, I went upstairs to go to bed, feeling quite sure by this time
Quequake must certainly have brought his Ramadan to a termination. But no, there
he was, just where I had left him. He had not stirred an inch. I began to grow
vexed with him. It seemed so downright senseless and insane to be sitting there
all day and half the night on his hams in a cold room holding a piece of wood
on his head. "For heaven's sake, Quiquay, get up and shake yourself. Get
up and have some supper. You'll starve.
You'll kill yourself," Quiquay. But not a word did he reply.
Desparing of him, therefore, I determined to go to bed and to sleep,
and no doubt before a great while he would follow me. But previous to turning
in, I took my heavy bare skin jacket and threw it over him, as it promised to be
a very cold night, and he had nothing but his ordinary round jacket on. For
some time, do all I would, I could not get into the faintest doze. I had blown
out the candle, and the mere thought of Quequ not four feet off, sitting there
in that uneasy position, stark alone in the cold and dark, this made me really
wretched. Think of it, sleeping all night in the same room with a wide awake
pagan on his hams in this dreary, unaccountable Ramadan.
But somehow I dropped off at last and knew nothing more till break of day,
when, looking over the bedside, there squatted Quiquake, as if he had been
screwed down to the floor. But as soon as the first glimpse of sun entered the
window, up he got with stiff and grating joints, but with a cheerful look, limp
towards me where I lay, pressed his forehead against mine, and said his Ramadan was over.
Now, as I before hinted, I have no objection to any person's religion, be
it what it may, so long as that person does not kill or insult any other
person, because that other person don't believe it also. But when a man's
religion becomes really frantic, when it is a positive torment to him, and in
fine makes this earth of ours an uncomfortable inn to lodge in, then I
think at high time to take that individual aside and argue the point
with him, and just so I now did with Quequ
said, I get into bed now and lie and listen with me. Then I went on beginning
with the rise and progress of the primitive religions and coming down to
the various religions of the present time during which time I labored to show
Quiquake that all these lents Ramadans and prolonged ham squattings and cold
cheerless rooms were stark nonsense, bad for the health, useless for the soul,
opposed in short to the obvious laws of hygiene and common sense. I told him too
that he being in other things such an extremely sensible and sagacious savage,
it pained me very badly pained me to see him now so deplorably foolish about this
ridiculous Ramadan of his. Besides, argued I, fasting makes the body cave
in, hence the spirit caves in, and all thoughts born of a fast must necessarily
be half starved. This is the reason why most dispic religionists cherish such
melancholy notions about their hereafters. In one word, Quiquake, said
I, rather digressively, hell is an idea first born on an undigested apple
dumpling, and since then perpetuated through the hereditary disps nurtured by Ramadans.
I then asked Quiquake whether he himself was ever troubled with dispsia,
expressing the idea very plainly so that he could take it in. He said, "No, only
upon one memorable occasion. It was after a great feast given by his father,
the king, on the gaining of a great battle, wherein 50 of the enemy had been
killed by about 2:00 in the afternoon, and all cooked and eaten that very
evening." "No more," Quiquig, said I, shuddering. "That will do, for I knew
the inferences without his further hinting them. I had seen a sailor who
had visited that very island, and he told me that it was the custom, when a
great battle had been gained there, to barbecue all the slain in the yard or
garden of the victor, and then one by one they were placed in great wooden
trenches, and garnished round like a pillow, with bread fruit and coconuts,
and with some parsley in their mouths, were sent round with the victor's
compliments to all his friends, just as though these presents were so many Christmas turkeys.
After all, I do not think that my remarks about religion made much of an
impression on Quiquake, because in the first place he somehow seemed dull of
hearing on that important subject, unless considered from his own point of
view, and in the second place he did not more than onethird understand me, couch
my ideas as simply as I would. And finally, he no doubt thought he knew a
good deal more about true religion than I did. He looked at me with a sort of
condescending concern and compassion, as though he thought it a great pity that
such a sensible young man should be so hopelessly lost to evangelical pagan
piety. At last we rose and dressed, and Quiquake, taking a prodigiously hearty
breakfast of chowers of all sorts, so that the landlady should not make much
profit by reason of his Ramadan. We sied out to board the Peekquad, sauntering
along and picking our teeth with halibet bones.